Guide to the Jared Treman Newman papers, 1803-1953.
Newman, Jared Treman papers, 1803-1953.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Jared Treman Newman papers, 1803-1953, 1803-1937 (bulk)
2157
Jared T. (Jared Treman) Newman, 1855-1937.
23.2 cubic ft.
Correspondence, legal documents, reports, accounts, blueprints, maps, clippings, and printed material.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Jared Treman Newman was an Ithaca, New York attorney, 1893-1896, and mayor, 1907-1908; Cornell University Trustee, 1895-1903 and 1907-1933; and a bank official.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Jared Treman Newman was an Ithaca, New York attorney, 1893-1896, and mayor, 1907-1908; Cornell University Trustee, 1895-1903 and 1907-1933; and a bank official.
Cornell University Class of 1875.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Papers include correspondence, legal documents, reports, accounts, blueprints, maps, clippings, and printed material dealing primarily with the interest of Newman and Charles H. Blood in the development of Cayuga Heights, but also with Renwick Heights and Bryant Park, Ithaca, New York; minutes of the organizational meeting of the Cayuga Heights Land Corporation, 1928. Also, letters and papers concerning banking institutions in Ithaca and elsewhere; real estate in South Dakota, Illinois, and Florida; other business concerns; the expansion and promotion of the New York State Barge Canal system; the affairs of Cascadilla School, Ithaca; alumni activities of the Cornell Class of 1875; manuscript and printed matter concerning the Ithaca Presbyterian Church, the Cornell University Christian Association, and Cornell United Religious Work; letter to Professor Floyd K. Richtmyer concerning his views of a proposed school of religion at Cornell; Newman's appointment as special lecturer in the Cornell Law School, 1897-1899; and his terms of service as a Trustee, including an Alumni Trustee Report, 1898. Also, correspondence with Wilmot Moses Smith, 1875; William Ozmun Wyckoff, 1891, concerning his interest in a Tompkins County, New York judgeship; a letter from Eugene Frayer concerning Cornell President Charles Kendall Adams; letters from George Lincoln Burr, Hiram Corson, Mina Miller Edison, Thomas Alva Edison, Leonard Knight Elmhirst, Livingston Farrand, and Harry Emerson Fosdick.
Additional correspondents include Frank Ernest Gannett, David Starr Jordan, Juliette Levy, Seymour Lowman, Albert Russell Mann, Nathan L. Miller, James Richard Robinson, Catherine Rumball, Nathaniel Schmidt, Jacob Gould Schurman, Alfred Emanuel Smith, Edwin Crowell Stuart, Frank Thilly, Robert Henry Treman, Andrew Dickson White, the Williams family, and Mung Yee Yap thanking "the good people of Ithaca" and Newman for the hospitality shown him during his student days at Cornell and mentioning impressions of Japan and descriptions of the Soochow School of Diplomacy and the Comparative Law School, both in Shanghai, China.
Family correspondence includes a letter from Joseph LaFayette LePine (Newman's great grandfather) to Margaret Kearney concerning the troubled conditions in Haiti, 1803; four items (1843) regarding an indemnity France paid to LePine's daughter Anna Marie Louise LePine Paddock Treman for losses suffered during the slave revolts in Haiti; and reminiscences (1889) of Adrianna Leonora Treman King. Papers of Newman's son, Charles H., include correspondence, reports, and memoranda (1917-1925) concerning his World War I service and veteran's claims; condolence letters received after his father's death; and correspondence with Gerald C. Williams, Frederick R. Stevens and others concerning biographical sketches of his father (1938 and 1953).
Detailed index available in accession folder.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Newman, Jared T. (Jared Treman), 1855-1937.; Adams, Charles Kendall, 1835-1902.; Blood, Charles H.; Burr, George Lincoln, 1857-1938.; Corson, Hiram, 1828-1911.; Edison, Mina Miller.; Edison, Thomas A. (Thomas Alva), 1847-1931.; Elmhirst, L. K. (Leonard Knight), 1893-1974.; Farrand, Livingston.; Fosdick, Harry Emerson, 1878-1969.; Frayer, Eugene.; Gannett, Frank E. (Frank Ernest), 1876-1957.; Jordan, David Starr, 1851-1931.; Kearney, Margaret.; King, Adrianna Leonora Treman.; LePine, Joseph LaFayette.; Levy, Juliette.; Lowman, Seymour.; Mann, Albert Russell, 1880-1947.; Miller, Nathan L.; Mung, Yee Yap.; Newman, Charles Hardy.; Richtmyer, F. K. (Floyd Karker), 1881-1939.; Robinson, James Richard.; Rumball, Catherine.; Schmidt, Nathaniel.; Schurman, Jacob Gould, 1854-1942.; Smith, Alfred Emanuel, 1873-1944.; Smith, Wilmot Moses.; Stevens, Frederick R.; Stuart, Edwin Crowell.; Thilly, Frank, 1865-1934.; Treman family.; Treman, Anna Marie Louise LePine.; Treman, Charles H.; Treman, Robert Henry.; White, Andrew Dickson, 1832-1918.; Williams family.; Williams, Gerald C.; Wyckoff, William Ozmun.; Cascadilla School.; Cayuga Heights Land Corporation.; Cornell University--Alumni and alumnae.; Cornell University--Religion.; Cornell University Christian Association.; Cornell University. Board of Trustees.; Cornell University. United Religious Work.; Ithaca Presbyterian Church (N.Y.).
Subjects:
Land use--New York (State)--Bryant Park.; Land use--New York (State)--Cayuga Heights.; Land use--New York (State)--Renwick Heights.; Real property, Exchange of--Florida.; Real property, Exchange of--Illinois.; Real property, Exchange of--South Dakota.; Religion.; World War, 1914-1918.; Lawyers.
Places:
New York State Barge Canal System (N.Y.); China.; Haiti.; Ithaca (N.Y.); Japan.
Form and Genre Terms:
Blueprints.; Maps.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
COLLECTION ARRANGEMENT
Arranged chronologically.
CONTAINER LIST
- Link to a partial finding aid.
  Contains a list of correspondents which can be cross-referenced to the years given below.
- May 1, 1855-Oct. 27, 1889 (Box 1)
- Oct. 28, 1889-Sept. 9, 1893 (Box 2)
- Sept. 11, 1893-May 31, 1894 (Box 3)
- June 1, 1894-Feb. 19, 1896 (Box 4)
- Feb. 20-Dec. 31, 1896 (Box 5)
- Jan. 1, 1897-July 15, 1901 (Box 6)
- July 16-Dec. 30, 1901 (Box 7)
- Jan. 2, 1902-Dec. 31, 1907 (Box 8)
- Jan. 1, 1908-Dec. 31, 1916 (Box 9)
- Jan. 1, 1917-Sept. 16, 1919 (Box 10)
- Sept. 17, 1919-Mar. 18, 1920 (Box 11)
- Mar. 19-Nov. 30, 1920 (Box 12)
- Dec. 1, 1920-June 14, 1921 (Box 13)
- June 15, 1921-June 30, 1922 (Box 14)
- July 1, 1922-July 16, 1923 (Box 15)
- July 18, 1923-Feb. 28, 1925 (Box 16)
- Mar. 1-Dec. 31, 1925, and misc. 1925 (Box 17)
- Jan. 1, 1926-Feb. 28, 1927 (Box 18)
- Mar. 1-Dec. 31, 1927, and general 1927 (Box 19)
- Jan. 1-Oct. 13, 1928 (Box 20)
- Oct. 16, 1928-Apr. 30, 1929 (Box 21)
- May 1-Dec. 31, 1929 (Box 22)
- Jan. 1-Sept. 30, 1930 (Box 23)
- Oct. 1, 1930-Jan. 14, 1931 (Box 24)
- Jan. 16-Sept. 30, 1931 (Box 25)
- Oct. 1, 1931-Apr. 13, 1932 (Box 26)
- Apr. 17-Nov. 29, 1932 (Box 27)
- Dec. 1, 1932-July 31, 1933 (Box 28)
- Aug. 1, 1933-May 31, 1934 (Box 29)
- June 1, 1934-Mar. 31, 1935 (Box 30)
- Apr. 1-Nov. 30, 1935 (Box 31)
- Dec. 1, 1935-July 31, 1936 (Box 32)
- Aug. 1, 1936-June 8, 1937 (Box 33)
- Cayuga Heights Development 1 (Box 34)
- Cayuga Heights Development 2 (Box 34)
- "The Community Farm" by "John Hallifax" (Box 34)
- Cornell University (Box 34)
- First National Bank of Ithaca, The Ithaca Savings Bank (Box 34)
- First Presbyterian Church of Ithaca (Box 34)
- Florida Real Estate (Box 34)
- General Undated Correspondence (alphabetical by sender) (Box 34)
- Ithaca Land Development - Berkshire Addition (Box 34)
- Ithaca Land Development - Bills and Receipts (Box 34)
- Ithaca Land Development - Klinewoods and Renwick Heights (Box 34)
- Ithaca Land Development - Miscellaneous Papers (Box 34)
- Ithaca Land Development - Taxation Papers (Box 34)
- Ithaca Land Development - White Park (Box 34)
- J.T. Newman's Reminiscences of Thomas A. Edison (Box 35)
- Miscellaneous Papers (Box 35)
- New York State Canals and Waterways (Box 35)
- Political Items (Box 35)
- Religious Studies and Addresses 1 (Box 35)
- Religious Studies and Addresses 2 (Box 35)
- Seattle, Washington, Land Development (Box 35)
- Seattle, Washington, Land Investments (Westlake Realty Company) (Box 35)
- Y.M.C.A. (Box 35)
- Cash Book - list of business transactions, Jan. 14, 1925-Jan. 8, 1934. (Box 36)
- Cash Account - list of receipts and disbursements, Mar. 20, 1907-Dec. 31, 1924. (Box 36)
- Cash and Land Accounts - Cayuga Heights Land Corporation, Jan. 10, 1929-July 1, 1933. (Box 36)
- Three "Commonplace Books," containing accounts of court cases, investments, estates, deeds, claims, mortgages, settlements, taxes, etc.
  - - first book - Jan. 12, 1915-Dec. 8, 1917 (Box 36)
  - - second book - Feb. 21, 1918-Apr. 3, 1919 (Box 36)
  - - third book - Nov. 1, 1919-Dec. 27, 1922 (Box 36)
- Ledger, Bryant Land Company, May 29, 1909-Jan. 7, 1918. (Box 36)
- Book of Expenses - partially filled, Jan. 10, 1929-Dec. 31, 1931. (Box 36)
- Checkbook - partially unused - from Cayuga Heights Land Co., Jan. 13, 1919-Oct. 14, 1933. (Box 36)
- Cash and Ledger Book, Jan. 1, 1920-June 30, 1950. (Box 37)
- Ledger - Charlotte E. Williams Estate, Mar. 17, 1927-Nov. 2, 1931, mainly RR, other securities. (Box 37)
- Account Book - Inventory & Transfer of Interests of the Estate of Charlotte E. Williams, Mar. 17, 1927-Nov. 2, 1931. (Box 37)
- Ledger - Cayuga Heights and others, Jan. 1, 1917-Jan. 25, 1936. (Box 37)
- Account Book - Business transactions; household and personal expenses, Jan. 23, 1932-Nov. 1, 1936. (Box 37)
- Two typed volumes on law and court procedure. (Box 37)
- Pamphlets, Newspaper Clippings and Broadside - not sorted. (Box 38)
- Who's Who in New York, 1952 - workroom shelves. (Box 38)
- Who's Who in the East, 1955 - reading room. (Box 38)
- Letters from Joseph LaFayette Lepine's generation to Jared Treman's generation (including death notices of Jared Treman and Abner Treman, his father), May 6, 1803-June 1898. (Box 39)
- Jared T. Newman's business letters and Charles H. Newman's World War I papers, Dec. 7, 1909-Dec. 11, 1925. (Box 39)
- Jared T. Newman's business letters and Presbyterian Church material, 1926-Nov. 16, 1935. (Box 39)
- Abstract of Correspondence between Jared T. Newman and Charles H. Blood from 1922 to 1936; and Mr. and Mrs. Jared T. Newman's Golden Anniversary clippings, and business letters, June 7, 1936-Oct. 22, 1936. (Box 39)
- Obituary notices and condolences for Jared T. Newman, May 11-June 10, 1937. (Box 39)
- Charles Newman's letters, and biographical notes about Jared T. Newman, Nov. 28, 1938-Feb. 20, 1953. (Box 39)
- Newsclippings. (Box 39)
- Jared T. Newman's address book and notes on travels, accounts, and numberous subjects. (Box 39)
- Gold ruler presented to J.T.N. for his efforts for the Cayuga Seneca Barge Canal, 1909. (Box 39)
- Sanborn map of Ithaca, N.Y., indexed in 26 sections in a bound volume. Placed in bottom a map drawer marked "maps 1-100". Map card made Jan. 29, 1965. (Box 39)
- Hon. Josiah Butler Williams' wedding record. (Box 39)
- Ithaca High School Twenty-Five Year Book 1876-1900 (taken out of the collection). (Box 39)